{"tossups": [{"question": "One painting from this artistic movement was considered sacrilegious because the carpentry shop it depicted was messy and Mary was unattractive. Along with Christ in the House of His Parents, another painting of Jesus from this movement depicts him knocking on a door and was entitled The Light of the World. The Germ magazine chronicled work from this movement, and Elizabeth (*) Siddal posed for in a river for Ophelia, a painting from this movement. For 10 points, name this movement whose founders William Holman Hunt, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and John Everett Millais were influenced by art from before the Renaissance.", "answer": "Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This leader promulgated a liberal legal code known as the Nakaz. This ruler signed the Treaty of Kucuk-Kaynarca following the Battle of Chesme, and later confined all Jewish subjects to the Pale of Settlement. This ruler placed (*) Stanislaw Poniatowski on the throne of a neighboring nation, and one advisor to this ruler created namesake sham villages on the Crimean peninsula. This lover of Grigory Potemkin and Grigory Orlov defeated the revolt of Yemelyan Pugachev, who pretended to be this woman\u2019s dethroned husband Peter III. For 10 points, name this long-serving \u201cenlightened\u201d Russian empress.", "answer": "Catherine the Great (prompt on \u201cCatherine\u201d)", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In one song, this singer notes \u201chow it\u2019s strange that some roots are like cages.\u201d In another, this artist sings of a young man sleeping \u201cby the bodegas and the lights on Upper Broadway.\u201d That track, \u201cDiamonds on the Soles of her Shoes,\u201d appears on his 1986 album (*) Graceland. This man\u2019s most famous collaboration produced the soundtrack for The Graduate and such hits as \u201cBridge over Troubled Water\u201d and \u2018The Sound of Silence.\u201d For ten points, name this American singer-songwriter who formed half of a namesake duo with Art Garfunkel.", "answer": "Paul Simon", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This man ordered that the wives of priests be enslaved at the Synod of Melfi. This man was opposed by Antipope Clement III, who held Rome during the entirety of this man\u2019s reign. This pope allied himself with Roger I of Sicily, and he was heavily influenced by a delegation sent by (*) Alexius I Komnenos. At the Council of Clermont, this pontiff proclaimed \u201cDeus Vult,\u201d or \u201cGod wills it,\u201d and urged Christian Europe to reclaim lost territory in the East. For ten points, name this eleventh century French Pope who launched the First Crusade.", "answer": "Pope Urban II (prompt on Urban)", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This man utilized the Schomburgk Line to quell a crisis in Venezuela, and he controversially opposed a train fare discount when governor of his home state. In the White House, this man refused to annex Hawaii, and his frequent use of the veto earned him the nickname \u201cHis Obstinacy.\u201d This man overcame a scandal involving (*) Maria Halpin to defeat James Blaine for the presidency, and while in office this man signed the Dawes Act and crushed the 1894 Pullman Strike. For ten points, name this Bourbon Democrat from New York, the only president to serve non-consecutive terms.", "answer": "Stephen Grover Cleveland (accept Grover Cleveland)", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In one work in this series, a man that is accused of stealing a bucket of nails drowns in order to avoid confessing to a crime he didn\u2019t commit. In another work in this series, a man wants to buy Sutter\u2019s land from the funds that the family would get from selling the title object, while his sister (*) Berenice Charles wants to keep the title object because of the carved faces of their family. In a work in this series, a man becomes the first black garbage truck driver in town. That play is about Troy Maxson. For ten points, name this series of works by August Wilson that all take place in the title Pennsylvanian city.", "answer": "The Pittsburgh Cycle", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In a work by this author, a father sentences his son to \u201cdeath by drowning.\u201d That work is \u201cThe Judgement.\u201d In a short story by this author, an officer attempts to have the words \u201cBe Just\u201d written on him, but is instead stabbed to death. In one of this author\u2019s novels, the final words of the central character are \u201cLike a dog!\u201d That character, (*) Josef K., is executed without knowing his crime. This author\u2019s most notable work is about a man who wakes up to find himself transformed into a giant insect. For ten points, name this author of \u201cIn the Penal Colony,\u201d The Trial, and The Metamorphosis.", "answer": "Franz Kafka", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s revolution began with the Cry of Pugad Lawin and was orchestrated by the Katipunan society. The Hukbalahap insurgency advocated for communism in this nation, whose first independent president was Manuel Quezon. An American occupation of this nation was resisted by the islamic Moro people and revolutionaries led by (*) Emilio Aguinaldo. In 1983, Benigno Aquino was assassinated upon returning to this county, an event which helped spark the People Power Revolution against this nation\u2019s dictator Ferdinand Marcos. For ten points, name this island nation of Southeast Asia with capital at Manilla.", "answer": "Philippines", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This film\u2019s pioneering style of composition and focus was orchestrated by Gregg Toland. The protagonist of this film loses both his marriage and a gubernatorial campaign after his affair with Susan Alexander is revealed, though Alexander eventually leaves him after an unhappy (*) opera career. The Xanadu estate is one setting for this movie, and the biggest mystery in this film is revealed by a sled being thrown into a furnace. For ten points, name this 1941 movie starring and directed by Orson Welles and whose titular newspaper mogul dies after saying \u201cRosebud.\u201d", "answer": "Citizen Kane", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "These compounds are reduced to aldehydes via the acid chloride in the Rosenmund reduction. In Barbier\u2013Wieland degradation, an aliphatic chain having a simple methylene bridge at the alpha position can be shortened by one carbon in these compounds. These compounds often have strong odors, especially the (*) volatile derivatives. These compounds easily dissociate because they are held together by resonance. These compounds include a hydroxyl group attached to the same carbon as a double-bonded oxygen. For ten points name this most common type of organic acid, with forms including maleic acid, citric acid, and acetic acid.", "answer": "carboxylic acids HALFTIME", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This person is credited with the phrase \u201cPandora\u2019s Box\u201d after a mistranslating Hesiod's Pandora. This thinker wrote Manual of a Christian Knight urging people to look beyond the rites of religion and penned Education of a Christian Prince as advice for Emperor Charles V. This man assessed the need for church reform in his Sileni Alcibiadis, though he condemned Martin Luther in his (*) De Libero Arbitrio. This man\u2019s most famous work satirizes Catholic doctrine and superstition through support for the titular being who is nursed by \u201cInebriation and Ignorance\u201d. For ten points, name this early Dutch Humanist and author of In Praise of Folly.", "answer": "Desiderius Erasmus", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In Xenopus embryos, sea urchin embryos, and Drosophila embryos, one phase in this process in functionally non-existent. The process is most affected when gene regulatory proteins of the E2F family have become unrestrained, causing cancerous replication. This process is initiated by the complex of cyclin D and CDK4/6. At the end of this phase, the cyclin (*) B-CDK1 complex activation causes breakdown of nuclear envelope and initiation of the next phase. This phase sees the replication of organelles and the genetic code preceding mitosis. For ten points, name this phase that a cell spends most of its life in that proceeds in three subphases, G1, S, and G2.", "answer": "interphase", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One novel from this country follows people looking for free will after the fall of their dictator, that novel is On Heroes and Tombs. It\u2019s not Italy, but another novel by an author from this country has instructions on how to read the novel in the beginning because of its \u201cexpendable chapters.\u201d In this home nation of Ernesto Sabato, Cat People, Paris Underground, and I Walked with a Zombie are some of the films that (*) Molina talks to Valentin about. Another author from this country talks about \u201cthe Purifiers\u201d in a short story about endless rooms. For ten points, name this Latin American country home to Julio Cort\u00e1zar, Manuel Puig, and Jorge Luis Borges.", "answer": "Argentina", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This novel begins with the firing of James Forster and the hiring of a servant whose watch is four minutes too slow. Near the end of this novel, the main character buys a boat to Liverpool, which he rips apart to fuel the boat. In this novel, a Parsee woman named Aouda is saved from being burnt to death in a Sati. (*) Detective Fix pursues this novel\u2019s protagonist throughout his journey to win a bet, which is won because of a miscalculation of the date. For ten points, name this Jules Verne novel about Passepartout and Phileas Fogg\u2019s journey to circumnavigate the globe.", "answer": "Around the World in Eighty Days", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In Hungarian mythology, Hadur is the god of this concept. One deity of this concept was hit in the face when a man became enraged and threw a bull\u2019s leg at her, and another deity of this event owns the Stymphalian birds. The Egyptian goddess of this event is named (*) Sekhmet and nearly destroyed all of humanity before Ra got her drunk. The Greek god of this concept was caught having an affair with Aphrodite by Hephaestus. For 10 points, name this concept, gods of which include the Babylonian Ishtar and the Greek Ares.", "answer": "war (or equivalents)", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "In quantum statistical mechanics, the thermal expectation value of this property is obtained by taking the negative partial derivative with respect to beta of log of the exponential trace of the Hamiltonian. In classical mechanics, the conservation of this property is guaranteed by (*) time translational symmetry through Noether\u2019s theorem. Quantum fields cannot attain 0 for their zero-point forms of this property due to the Uncertainty Principle. In particle physics, the vacuum form of this property causes the Lamb Shift in the spectral lines of hydrogen. For ten points, name this property whose rest form in special relativity is equivalent to mass times the speed of light squared.", "answer": "energy", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Members of the Baha\u2019i faith perform this action over the nineteen days before their new year.  Sikh doctrine says that those who perform this action \u201care rewarded with less than a shell,\u201d and this practice is not performed in Zoroastrianism due to the belief that it weakens the soul and devotion to god by weakening the (*) body. Jews perform this practice during Yom Kippur, and certain Christians choose to do it during Lent. For 10 points, name this practice that, per the fourth pillar of Islam, Muslims must engage in during daylight hours of Ramadan.", "answer": "fasting (accept sufficient descriptions such as not eating, prompt on \u2018Sawm\u2019)", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "The Serra da Estrela is the primary mountain range of this country. The tourist rich Algarve region makes up the south of this country which is home to imposing cliffs along Cape St. Vincent and Gustave Eiffel\u2019s Dom Luis Bridge in Porto. The Tagus River flows through this European country which controls the (*) Madeiras and the Azores. The largest city in this country contains the Pra\u00e7a do Com\u00e9rcio and survived a massive 1755 earthquake and tsunami. For ten points, name this non-Spanish country on the Iberian Peninsula whose capital is Lisbon.", "answer": "Portugal", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "Isopach maps are used to determine the thickness of deposits created by these entities, which can produce sideromelane, an uncommon form of tachylite that forms hyaloclastite deposits. Elliptically shaped coul\u00e9es form on the flanks of these entities, whose products mix with groundwater to create maars. These entities can trigger (*) j\u00f6kulhlaups, and, when located beneath a glacier, are called mobergs or tuyas. Tephra and lahars of pyroclasts are emitted from these entities, which can also produce pahoehoe and \u2018a\u2019a. For 10 points, name these geologic structures which come in submarine, shield, and cinder-cone types from which lava erupts.", "answer": "volcanoes", "subcategory": "Science Other", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This piece uses eleven bars of pizzicato and thirty second notes to create different types of rain. Jean-Jacques Rousseau arranged a flute solo for this work, which was released in 1725 with accompanying sonnets. In one part of this work, a viola plays \u201calways forte\u201d to replicate the barking of the goatherd\u2019s dog while another part of this work depicts a (*) sleeping shepherd. Cuckoo calls and drunken dances are imitated in this work, which is included in its composer\u2019s Contest Between Harmony and Invention. For 10 points, name this set of four violin concertos by Antonio Vivaldi which includes \u201cSpring\u201d and \u201cWinter.\u201d", "answer": "The Four Seasons", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In one work set in this place, Comstock works in a small bookshop and works to write a magnum opus called this place\u2019s \u201cpleasures.\u201d Comstock\u2019s only published work, a collection of poetry entitled Mice, is completely neglected. Another work set in this place includes a convict who is given a reprieve by \u201cpleading her belly\u201d to get out of (*) Newgate Prison. This place was fled by a character who brutally murders his lover Nancy and works under Fagin. One address in this place first appears in A Study in Scarlet, that address is 221 Baker Street. For ten points, name this city paired with Paris in A Tale of Two Cities.", "answer": ": London, England Bonuses", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "This nonfiction work set in Holcomb, Kansas is considered the first in the true crime genre. For ten points each:", "answers": ["In Cold Blood", "Truman Capote", "geisha"], "parts": ["Name this novel about Perry Smith and Dick Hickock\u2019s murders of the Clutter family.", "This author wrote In Cold Blood and Breakfast at Tiffany\u2019s.", "Capote calls the protagonist of Breakfast at Tiffany\u2019s an American example of a member of this profession."], "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "RNA interference was first discovered in this model organism. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["Caenorhabditis elegans", "apoptosis", "caspases (accept cysteine-aspartic proteases or cysteine aspartases)"], "parts": ["Name this nematode, the first multicellular organism to have its genome sequenced.", "The genes ced-3 and ced-4, discovered in C. elegans, are key to this process. This process occurs 131 times in C. elegans cells.", "These protease enzymes with a cysteine at their active site play an important role in apoptosis."], "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "For ten points each, name these Caribbean authors.", "answers": ["V. S. Naipaul", "Aime Cesaire", "Jamaica Kincaid (accept Elaine Potter Richardson)"], "parts": ["This Trinidadian author wrote a novel about a man with an inauspicious birth in A House for Mr. Biswas.", "This Negritude author from Martinique wrote a work that sympathetically portrays Caliban as a black slave and casts Ariel as a Mulatto in Une Temp\u00eate.", "This Antiguan woman took ten pen name \u201cJamaica\u201d when she published Lucy and Annie John."], "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following about the anti-communist revolutions of 1989. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Solidarity", "Berlin Wall", "Romania"], "parts": ["1989\u2019s revolutionary wave began in Poland with the dramatic victory of this Polish labor union led by Lech Wa\u0142\u0119sa. Long banned, this party forced free elections in which it won 99 out of 100 possible seats.", "While communist regimes toppled around the world, this German Cold War landmark stood until November 1989, when a confusing statement by G\u00fcnter Schabowski caused protesters to tear it down piece by piece.", "Perhaps the final geopolitical drama of 1989 occurred in this nation, where strongman Nicolae Ceau\u015fescu and his wife Elena were overthrown on December 22 and executed on Christmas Day."], "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This war was supposed to be avoided through the First and Second Partition Treaties. For ten points each:", "answers": ["War of the Spanish Succession", "Louis XIV (prompt on partial answer)", "John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough"], "parts": ["Name this 13-year conflict over control of an Iberian nation. It was sparked by the death of the childless King Charles II.", "The War of the Spanish Succession pitted Austria, Britain, and Prussia against this French \u201csun king\u201d who wanted his grandson Philip to claim the Spanish crown.", "During the conflict, Allied forces were led by Eugene of Savoy and this wealthy British noble. His victories at Blenheim and Malplaquet helped maintain the fragile anti-French alliance."], "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "One work by this composer begins with a march of pilgrims moving through the mountains, and ends with the \u201cOrgy of the Brigands.\u201d For ten points each:", "answers": ["Hector Berlioz", "Symphonie Fantastique", "\u201cMarch to the Scaffold\u201d"], "parts": ["Name this composer of Les Troyens and Harold in Italy.", "Berlioz\u2019s most famous work was this program symphony, premiered in 1830. The psychedelic nature of this work leads some to believe Berlioz wrote it under the influence of opium.", "This is the penultimate section of Symphonie Fantastique, which ends with a four-bar recollection of the id\u00e9e fixe in a solo clarinet."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about an important technique in chemistry. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["electrolysis (do not accept \u201celectrology\u201d)", "oxidation (prompt on \u201credox\u201d or \u201coxidation-reduction\u201d)", "decomposition potential (accept decomposition voltage)"], "parts": ["This process, named by Michael Faraday in 1833, uses current to activate a chemical reaction. Many Group 1 and Group 2 elements were discovered using this technique.", "During electrolysis, this reaction can occur at an anode. Examples include ferrous ions becoming ferric ions following the loss of an electron.", "This value is the minimum voltage needed between the anode and cathode of the electrolytic cell in order for electrolysis to occur."], "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This scientist\u2019s namesake modulus is the ratio of stress to strain in a material. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["Thomas Young", "bulk modulus", "Sim\u00e9on Denis Poisson"], "parts": ["Name this physicist who conducted the double-slit experiment.", "This other modulus is the reciprocal of compressibility. It is the ratio of the infinitesimal pressure increase to the relative volume decrease.", "The shear modulus is the elastic modulus over one plus this mathematician's namesake ratio. He also names an equation stating that the Laplacian of potential equals negative charge density over permittivity."], "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "Marcel Mauss uses the term <em>hau</em> to describe the force that bind people involved with this practice. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Potlatch", "Bronis\u0142aw Malinowski", "Oedipus complex"], "parts": ["Name this system of gift exchange common among tribes of the Pacific Northwest. Franz Boas famously studied this system among the Kwakiutl tribe.", "This anthropologist explored the potlatch-style economics of the Kula Ring among inhabitants of the Trobriand Islands. This man also used his observations of the Trobriand islanders to write Coral Gardens and Their Magic.", "Malinowski challenged the universality of this Freudian concept, linking it to power rather than sexual envy."], "category": "Social Science"}, {"leadin": "This empire\u2019s leaders claimed descent from the sun god Inti. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Incan Empire", "Viracocha", "Supay"], "parts": ["Name this Quechoa-speaking empire with capital at Cuzco that was conquered by Francisco Pizarro.", "The Incans worshipped many gods including this creator deity who wears the sun as a crown and has thunderbolts for hands.", "This Incan god of the underworld has a name meaning \u2018devil\u2019. A dance for this god is performed during the Mamacha Candicha ritual."], "category": "Mythology"}, {"leadin": "The gene for sickle-cell anemia confers partial resistance to this disease because carriers lack the Duffy antigen. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["malaria", "Plasmodium", "artemisinins (accept qinghao su, accept sweet wormwood or Artemisia annua)"], "parts": ["Name this disease transmitted by the Anopheles mosquito.", "Malaria is caused by parasitic protozoans in this genus, which includes ovale and falciparum species.", "This group of drugs, superior to quinine, is used to treat Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Tu Youyou won the 2015 Nobel Prize in Medicine for its discovery."], "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "The characters of this sculpture carry keys in their hands. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Burghers of Calais", "Auguste Rodin", "The Age of Bronze"], "parts": ["Name this sculpture depicting six French noblemen surrendering themselves to Edward III.", "The Burghers of Calais was sculpted by this French artist of The Kiss and The Thinker.", "Rodin also sculpted this life-size statue of an ancient man running his hand through his hair. The popularity of this piece was buoyed by claims that Rodin cast it from a live model."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "The Macclesfield Bank is located in this body of water. For ten points each:", "answers": ["South China Sea", "Spratly Islands (accept Nansha Islands)", "Philippines"], "parts": ["Name this large sea in East Asia central to world trade and riddled with territorial disputes. Many conflicts in this body of water pit Vietnam against the country from which it takes its name.", "This archipelago in the South China Sea is the focal point for most conflict in the area. Larger than the Paracel Islands, these islands\u2019 strategic value comes in part from their considerable oil deposits.", "This country bounds the South China Sea to the west and contests the Scarborough Shoal. This country refers to much of the South China Sea as the Luzon Sea in reference to its largest island."], "category": "Geography"}, {"leadin": "On October 14, 2017, this man was expelled from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Harvey Weinstein", "#MeToo (with or without hashtag is acceptable)", "Mark Halperin"], "parts": ["Name this disgraced film mogul who was fired from his namesake company after scores of women accused him of sexual harassment and assault.", "Weinstein\u2019s fall sparked this online movement to expose similar predators and reveal the scope of sexual misconduct in contemporary America.", "This former MSNBC political analyst and author of Game Change issued an apology after over a dozen women accused him of harassment in the aftermath of the Weinstein scandal."], "category": "Trash"}, {"leadin": "One character in this work struggles with his obligation to kill Bhishma and Drona. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Bhagavad Gita", "Arjuna", "Kurukshetra War (accept Battle of Kurukshetra)"], "parts": ["Name this 700 verse Sanskrit poem from the Mahabharata, a dialogue between a Pandava prince and his charioteer Lord Krishna.", "This son of Indra is the main character of the Bhagavad Gita. In the Mahabharata, this man and his allies defeat the Kauravas.", "Arjuna\u2019s victory over the Kauravas comes during this 18-day conflict. Despite millions of participants, only twelve major warriors survived this war, including Satyaki and Yuyutsu."], "category": "Mythology"}, {"leadin": "Though often overshadowed, women made many meaningful contributions to the American Civil Rights Movement. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Rosa Parks", "Fannie Lou Hamer", "Shirley Chisholm"], "parts": ["This NAACP secretary sparked the Montgomery Bus Boycott by refusing to give up her seat to a white passenger in 1955.", "During the 1964 Democratic Convention, this woman and vice-chair of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party gave a stirring account of her treatment in the Jim Crow South.", "In 1968, this New York legislator became the first African American women elected to Congress, and later finished fourth in the 1972 Democratic presidential primaries."], "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "Moving between different levels of the afterlife and realm of the gods is a theme in multiple works of literature. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Don Juan", "Paradiso (prompt on \u201cParadise\u201d)", "Paradise Lost"], "parts": ["This character leaves heaven for a lower place because he is bored in George Bernard Shaw's play Man and Superman. This fictional libertine first appeared in a play by Tirso de Molina.", "This sphere that uses celestial bodies to represent different types of virtue represents heaven in Dante\u2019s Divine Comedy. It is contrasted with the Inferno and Purgatorio.", "In this work by John Milton, Lucifer is cast from heaven after staging a war with god and the angels."], "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "In this novel, a character is asked what makes someone a gentleman, to which he replies dignity. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Remains of the Day", "Kazuo Ishiguro", "The Buried Giant"], "parts": ["Name this novel about Stevens, a British butler who comes to work under Mr. Farraday.", "This British author of Japanese extraction wrote The Remains of the Day. In 2017, he won the Nobel Prize in Literature.", "This most recent Ishiguro novel was published in 2015 and focuses on the life of Axl and Beatrice, a couple living in Arthurian times."], "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about a type of religious music. For ten points each:", "answers": ["hymn (prompt on \u201cspiritual\u201d)", "\u201cAmazing Grace\u201d", "\"A Mighty Fortress is Our God\""], "parts": ["Name this category of song written to reflect praise of or belief in a God or deity. Ancient examples include the Vedas in Hinduism and the Psalms in Judaism.", "This Christian hymn was penned by John Newton, a former slave trader who thanked God for \u201csaving a wretch like me.\u201d President Obama famously sang this hymn during a 2015 memorial service.", "This 16th century hymn by Martin Luther compares God to a \u201cbulwark, never failing.\u201d Luther and his allies allegedly sang this hymn while entering the Diet of Worms."], "category": "Religion"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about the Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Hern\u00e1n Cort\u00e9s", "Moctezuma II", "La Noche Triste (accept the Sad Night, or the Night of Sorrows)"], "parts": ["The conquest of the Aztecs was led by this conquistador from Medell\u00edn. After crushing the Aztecs and founding Mexico City, this man became the first Governor of New Spain.", "Early in his campaign, Cort\u00e9s captured this Aztec emperor and attempt to rule Mexico through him. The details of this man\u2019s captivity and eventual death remain unclear.", "After Moctezuma\u2019s death, Cort\u00e9s attempted to flee the Aztec capital in this event, but suffered heavy losses and a personal wound while doing so."], "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "Many important borders are distinguished by latitudinal parallels. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Korea", "Calvert Family", "Oregon Territory"], "parts": ["The 38th Parallel divides this peninsula into communist and democratic halves. In 1950, Kim Il-sung\u2019s army crossed the 38th Parallel, beginning a war named for this region.", "39 degrees and 43 minutes is the approximate latitude of the Mason-Dixon Line, which was intended to settle a dispute between Pennsylvania and this family of early Maryland governors.", "American expansionists like James Polk demanded that the latitude 54\u00b040' define the boundary between the U.S. and Britain in this northwestern region."], "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}]}